Tad Miyashita Papers
Tad Miyashita Papers
1952-1977
Miyashita, Tad,1922-1979.
3 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter. Collection includes artwork (both original and photographs), biographical material, correspondence, and printed material (exhibit catalogs, clippings, etc.).
149316
Biographical History
Tad Miyashita (1922-1979) was an American artist particularly known for his collage and his mixed-media and found object work. Born in Hawaii, he studied at the Corcoran School of Art in Washington, D.C. and at the Art Students League in New York City. During World War II he served with the Nisei Regimental Combat Team. He was a resident artist at the Millay Colony for the Arts (1975) and at Yaddo, and his work has been exhibited at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, the Grand Central Art Galleries, and the Corcoran Gallery among others in both solo and group shows.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Tad Miyashita Papers consist of artwork, biographical material, correspondence, and printed material.
Artwork contains one original piece (a collage) and numerous reproductions in the form of photographs, negatives, slides, and a few glass plate positives. Many of the slides were submissions to art galleries, competitions, or artists' colonies such as Yaddo.
Biographical material includes curriculum vitae and photographs of Miyashita, some by Dena.
Correspondence is the largest part of the collection, and consists entirely of incoming correspondence. Here may be found letters from friends and family (brother Toshio and various people who address him as "Uncle Tad"); colleagues in the creative arts, including poets, artists, and authors (Heather McHugh, Paul Friedman, Thomas McKeown, Nita Regnier, Frances Whyatt); art galleries (Grand Central Galleries, the Guggenheim, Whitney Museum of American Art); and residential artists' colonies where Miyashita stayed (Ossabaw Island Project, the Macdowell Colony, Yaddo). The most substantial correspondent is Paul Friedman, author and professor of English at the University of Illinois (four folders spanning 1973-1977).
Printed material contains exhibit catalogs for Miyashita and others, a number of books given to Miyashita by the authors (many of which are signed and inscribed to him), and a few miscellaneous items.
Arrangement of the Collection
Artwork is arranged alphabetically by type. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Printed material is arranged alphabetically by type and within that by title, if appropriate.
Related Material
has the papers of many important American artists and illustrators. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Art -- Sculptors; Canaday, John, 1907-; English, Maurice.; Friedman, Paul, 1937-; Humble, Christopher.; Launois, Yukiko.; Miyashita, Tad, 1922-1979.; Whyatt, Frances.; Yeh, Carol.; MacDowell Colony (Peterborough, N.H.); Yaddo (Artists' colony); Art, American -- 20th century.; Artist colonies -- United States.; Collage, American -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Poets, American.; Clippings (information artifacts); Collages (visual works); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Exhibition catalogs.; Negatives (photographs); Photographs.; Slides (photographs); Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Bulk of collection, gift of Tad Miyashita, 1967-1977.
Original collage, gift of Andrew Gurian, 2017.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Collage, "Wind on the Sand", original collage by Miyashita (Oversize 1)
    Gift of Andrew Gurian, 2017.
  - Glass plate positives (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Miyashita's work, includes prints and negatives (Box 1)
  - Slides, submitted to Gerald Brummer, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Slides, submitted to Guggenheim, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Slides, submitted to [Hawaii] State Foundation for Culture and the Arts, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Slides, submitted to Yaddo, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Slides, miscellaneous, undated; 1 item (Box 1)
- Biographical material
  - Curriculum vitae, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Abramowicz, Janet, 1966; 1977 (Box 1)
  - Adams, John and Margrit, 1975-1977; includes slides (Box 1)
  - Alexius, Paul, 1966-1972; 1975-1976; envelopes have return address "A. Burgess" (Box 1)
  - Asia Society, 1968-1969; 1972 (Box 1)
  - A, misc (Box 1)
  - Barrow, John, 1974; 1976 (Box 1)
  - B, misc (Box 1)
  - Canaday, John, See New York Times.
  - Creative Artists Public Service Program (CAPS), 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - C-D, misc (Box 1)
  - English, Maurice, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - E, misc (Box 1)
  - Friedman, Paul, 1973 (Box 1)
    See also Printed material: Books: Friedman, Paul.
  - Friedman, Paul, 1974-1977; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - F, misc (Box 2)
  - George Arents Research Library, See Syracuse University
  - Grand Central Art Galleries, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Grand Central Moderns, 1966 (Box 2)
    See also Roberts, Colette.
  - Guggenheim Museum / Guggenheim Foundation, 1968-1969; 1972,; 1975,; 1977 (Box 2)
  - Hanson, Pauline (Polly), See Yaddo; Printed material: Books: Hanson, Pauline
  - [Hawaii] State Foundation on Culture and the Arts, 1971-1974 (Box 2)
  - Holty, Carl, 1966; 1968,; 1972 (Box 2)
  - Honolulu Academy of Arts, 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Hough, Julia, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Humble, Christopher, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
  - H-I, misc (Box 2)
  - J, misc (Box 2)
  - Kamiya, Emi, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - K, misc (Box 2)
  - Landolt, Evan, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Launois, Yukiko, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Leiber, Judy and Gerson (Gus), 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - L, misc (Box 2)
  - Macdowell Colony, 1972-1977 (Box 2)
  - McHugh, Heather, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
    See also Printed material: Books: McHugh, Heather
  - McKeown, Thomas S., 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Millay Colony for the Arts, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Miyashita, Toshio [brother], 1966; 1970-1971; includes photographs (Box 2)
  - M, misc (Box 2)
  - Nakamura, Ed, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - New York Times, 1966-1972; undated; almost all are from John Canaday (Box 3)
  - Nishimoto, Joe and Maude, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - N, misc (Box 3)
  - Ossabaw Island Project, 1972-1973; 1977 (Box 3)
  - Peters, Bob, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - P, misc (Box 3)
  - Rapée, Joellen (Jody Hall; Mrs. George Rapée), 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Regnier, Nita, 1974; includes photocopy of short story, "Genesis Again" (Box 3)
  - Roberts, Colette, 1966; 1971 (Box 3)
  - R, misc (Box 3)
  - Sachs Gallery, 1967-1969 (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University, 1966-1977 (Box 3)
  - S, misc (Box 3)
  - Takashigi, Matt, 1966-1972; includes family members Anne, Sara, Hanna and Janet (Box 3)
  - Tsumura, Robert, 1971 (Box 3)
  - T, misc (Box 3)
  - Wada family, 1967-1977; includes Steve, Jenny, Steff, Taxie [?]; some original artwork by Jenny (Box 3)
  - Ward, Bruce and Patricia, 1970-1973; 1977 (Box 3)
  - West, Eleanor, See Ossabaw Island Project; Printed material: Books: West, Eleanor.
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1965-1969; 1972,; 1974 (Box 3)
  - Whyatt, Frances, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    See also Printed material: Books: Whyatt, Frances.
  - W, misc (Box 3)
  - Yaddo, 1973-1977 (Box 3)
  - Yeh, Carol, 1973-1977 (Box 3)
  - Yrisarry, Mario, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Y, misc (Box 3)
  - First name only (Box 3)
  - Unidentified or illegible (Box 4)
- Printed material
  - Books
    - Friedman, Paul, And If Defeated, Allege Fraud, 1971; signed and inscribed by author to TM (Box 4)
    - Hanson, Pauline (Polly), Across Countries of Anywhere, 1971; signed and inscribed by author to TM (Box 4)
    - McHugh, Heather, Dangers, 1977; signed and inscribed by author to TM (Box 4)
    - Roberts, Colette, Nevelson, 1965; signed and inscribed by author to TM (Box 4)
    - West, Eleanor, Maria Bosomworth and William Rodgers, 1976; signed by author with note to TM (Box 4)
    - Whyatt, Frances, Equal Time, 1977; signed and inscribed by author to TM (Box 4)
    - [unidentified, in Japanese] (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1958; 1965-1967 (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1975; 1977 (Box 5)
  - Exhibit catalogs, announcements, Miyashita, 1952-1953; 1958-1959,; 1963-1969; includes printed fabric banner; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Exhibit catalogs, announcements, others, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, pubilcity brochure featuring Miyashita collage on cover; booklet on U.S. - Japan Security treaty (Box 5)